Welcome back to build twenty fifteen this is the internet of things show
alive and I'm larry larson join hundred-year gavin
...to share on the...windows of
...devices peep brown I work on apps for musicians and
io to devices and...on our...your io together.
Great so, let's talk about some of the announcements that we've had this week so
...all join here altering makes it easy to interoperate with
...devices we built into windows ten and we had some your business
...onstage announcing...integration for their...to.
The scoliosis that we...what have.
Rate...availability of raspberry...windows builds...from...
max cool stuff we can play with renounce partnerships yesterday with our do we know with raspberry
...foundation...captured...great and what is the device that you've gotten
...your...this devices an enterprise quality of
...industrial robot
actually used to make automobiles believe it or not what it's got a couple motors inside here it's got
...reply on top of I have a universal windows application that drives
this thingthree I opens on my raspberry pi I can make it go forward I can make go back and
...xbox controller...this thing so we've got it upstairs for folks
here the conference...of mess around with them learn how to...
That's all csharp...on that it's all csharp code the apps that we've kind
...written all csharp code but in fact since it's universal windows
platform provided cplus-plus...any...language.
Great so we'll be taking your questions live to so if you go to
chow mein page scroll download the player and...your questions and...those...
So, gavin
tells a little bit more about what went on this week and what other things were going to be talking about
...perspective on all dryness technology and here to talk about so
...little...than year-ago microsoft...them all seen alliance
all seen alliances the organization around all during which is and opensource
cross-platform device communication framework and it's the largest
open-source code base that we've built into windows we built into windows ten
...really easy to write universal windows apps that can connect
...discover consumer to devices in-home setting something about
...so that's a little bit about what I've been up to the same even do some
constant...we haverecently announced not just the...righty services
but,...upcoming address...sweep is a set of apps that developers can provision
quickly get started with the proof of concept of for free
...take that same solution and scale it up to extreme...
Great so we've got a question from james
c says if using art window with windows stand especial hardware require.
Easy enough that's...that's...
So, what I'll show this a little bit my session...a few hours this afternoon well,
the way we've implemented this is I can taken
...we know which typically the microcontroller based
...so doesn't run windows it doesn't run any operating system in fact and,
I could take that are tweet on that I compared to windows device and I...get the best of both worlds I can use my
art...to really drive hardware very deterministic in ...
secure reliable way...I can use windows offload all the processing if I wanted to speak all
join from...talk to the cloud I can use windows problem those capabilities and
we've made a really easy to talk back and forth between...devices...windows device so steve
if someone is going to write codes can control robot like this tell me about the developer experience
where would you start assuming in visual studio team being...cool things because that's just?
Video...start by that building universal application we've got a we've got a
small some small sdk extensions
the people can use to get some of the very coyotes specific stuff but,
the idea is if you...to build the napping windows your now and I ot
developer you pretty much know which need to know learn a little bit about how to drive the...and how to do
...of the hardware other than that...windows developer your night?
Right...another question from our...much online viewer thanks for watching...how does one
...work with things like dpiwm and fbi.
...implemented as a universal windows platform api so I
from within the context of a...a I can I can access
ppi can access I squared see I can get it all the buses that I would expect to get
too the other thing that we're working on although we're not releasing this of build...be
...probably a couple months out is support for art we know wiring within
mywithin my universal...so if I don't want to use you know,
w pr want to bring language that I've got community existing are
...sketch I can easily go do that run that as well that needed supporters really awesome because,
you know, compared to imbedded linux development on raspberry pie for instance it's really easy to do a
bunch of stuff but to find dpi or code that would work I had to get some code off the internet and
had...is...so to have you know, namespaces that you can just enumerating your code...use
...sense I'm really looking forward to playing with that actually totally fucked, yeah,
so, one of the things that are one of our partners is working on...it is building upon that
to add-in support for gadget here on top of those same api so if you're familiar with
a micro frameworks that...the same shields the same devices the same
sensors and everything but it shows how complete this api said is that we can build
oct right on top of that just like we are without...here the show were showing all drawing support
in core which is the sort of lean and mean version of all joint running on dot net
...shown early preview at when hack and now they've actually got it running up and move so it's very fully
features that are team is working on doing the work in dot net micro framework to make sure that the
...api compatibility between the code I would write for very small microcontroller device
and dot micro framework and take exactly that same code run it on a larger device
with a full...cortex a powered cpu great compete what are the where the boards your
...I brought toys right so now the school as
the industrial robot over here but so one of the partner secret labs just announced the net we know
three wi-fi and ethernet this week which are big deal because he specifically looking at you know,
better asher integration for this so having onboard wi-fi is obviously quite important for doing
that and having onboard ethernet like a good solid networking stack there is good the other thing I
...is the prototype shield are prototype hat for of raspberry
...to the...worked on...let use all you gazetteer stuff and they also did a smaller
...that they're working on here that has all the
...built-in so-if you want-to do like an as your coyote demo that has you know,
temperature and light...and all that stuff just pop this in use the api
that you guys of written and then you're able to access leisure and, upload all that?
We've got a bunch of questions...from phillip what are the limitation seizing windows
...imc device what anti idea...
Difference between windows...core which is the
sm version of windows optimized for these devices and windows mobile
...or the enterprise version of windows for large devices
...there's no shell so there's no windows experience there's no start menu the
...from my...in fact I do have ahead I can implement this is a
...screen as well...I do have ahead the...my app is the app I wrote
...define the personality for my device things you would expect because there's no
shelters that in-box applications so I don't get the travel up and I don't get, you know, the mail
...things like that other than that it's a complete version of windows including,
you know, I get the identity model I get the security model I get
the enterprise manageability actually so everything these things can do windows update everything that needs
...a windows computer is supported by windows
ten-ninety core because it's built on core there's common platform, you know,
we showed writing lighting control...that would deployed to guzman
...max running windows...for small devices same app deployed local in your
dev box runs the same like you said the shell is the ui
...app so that the whole universal windows app model with uw
...is...this is a huge part of that story that's
right scales across bothwindows additions, you know, I can run on a desktop or phone
...small...server and xbox a hollow
...and also different hardware platforms I can target arm...can target x...you know,
switch back and forth very readily zero changes...literally just change that.
India audio session yesterday so
...was able to show taking a regular usb device that uses...new media
stacked that's in windows ten unplugging from the pc right disco plug it right into the raspberry
...deploy to the...just ran so I think that's really the our so
...tells about the video that we saw on the keno...some of the things that were in that video that
...done that was probably one of my favorite days on campus here we
spent a couple of days going around ...that you guys work in you know,
filming all the people that are doing great
...stuff so we saw lots of offices full of oscilloscope and toys
and robots and you know, the stuff that went into building...be
fifteen robot that showed up in the keno yesterday...pollens robot on all the work that
...was doing on the hardware for that absolutely amazing stuff that we're seeing in
there and what was really interesting about all those interviews is the building is just full of
makers like everybody there is not just doing this for their job but it's their passion
it's something that they do at night when they get home...lose work
...robots at...a person who you know,
created the first modern extruded...for three-d printers like...current way that it's
routing is done there so these are guys that are really, really into this and
...was a really fun video to record too much to say...too much ari from bill
...what are some where some places to go to find io tickets to get started with?
Gosh, lots of options out there so ...for the windows platform worship
forty-two hardware platforms today one of the raspberry...to the others them...max which
runs and intel x eighty-six cpu because it's because it's raspberry
...were trying to support a lot of the existing hardware ecosystem for...so I can
by whether shields and sensors and I can just use those things our dwindle makes
...giant...out on so I can use and different kids that I can use to
...building robots building temperature sensors for my garden...you know,
lots of crazy applications I was
I couple days ago I...down I was short on some...this is the other bad thing about being...
you're like man I don't have wire so you know, whatever across the street there's a radio shack I
went the bottom parts and I was amazed they have like a whole pile of kits.
Different kinds of sensors wires are twitter...and it's easy to get.
All right from dan how many different ot devices well-run windows ten on launch.
That ...launch so we haven't we haven't disclose the exact number boards
...support launch today it's raspberry...too and it's been aboard
...lots of other partners working with working very closely with qualcomm
...dragon board that's one that we hope to support
my launch a couple other partners that I can't talk about yet that
obviously the goal is to maximize the number of...market number of
...systems on a...and market that will support running windows
...is a great place to start...you want to get started now from
chris what cool ioc projects have you guys built at least that you could share with us?
...look, at up there's something going on there so,
it's fun stuff so I've started working with using windows on raspberry
...as the brains of synthesizers, yeah, so,
that's really not being able to take the type of app that are run on a tablet...being able to
embed that into a synthesizer the keyboard knobs and all that stuff is what I'm really interested in we
built some silly projects like I did they I...moisture
center built a diaper monitor shortly after my kids were born unfortunate it's like two big
spikes they come through and that doesn't go over too well with like my family when I did that, come on.
The kids...alarm anyway as I...of...trafficking kick-start,
yeah, that might be really good for that a good market there maybe the adult version of them so,
there's those things with lots of robots I think all of us here built umpteen thousand different types of
robots and stuff but most I'm really interested in like all the things that are existing
dot net developer community has built in terms of devices like people are doing home automation
with micro framework or with our...we know and stuff and they're doing, you know, things like garage
...simple things like garage door openers but they're not limited by what you can go on
buying a store they just like, you know, what I don't see exactly what I want the store I'm...to go make it and they get
a done it takes them a day or two to get it done they have that in their house or able to user I think
...with the stuff that's going on with all join...the stuff that's going on with asher between the two
of those things and...devices that were coming out with I think people are going to be
...make some really fantastic stuff over the next six months so really
excited any other projects on campus that we can talk about?
...we could talk and...actually it's quite active and build
...custom...they took one of the...printing platforms apart and
built the turntable scanner that we're showing here we're using a connect
me to which that's three-d scanning functionalities actually built into our three-d builder apps
you can very quickly get full color free model yourself so if you are maker though
and you're walking through buildings and microsoft there are places where you're just like wow what is
that what...one of the work and there's so many.
Different projects it...team we are
...end up with this stuff and it there was a day where I walk into the bathroomand, I
...click.
And, there's this...counting aggressive egress into the
into the restroom and I think they were just kind of testing sensors and they thought this would
be anyway I think ultimately after a few days create the team out there
...cannot the bathroom...kitchen or something
...that was that was the tools project but it was perhaps was disconcerting project
fans so larry one of the things that we just did for this keno I is one of the
makers that says part of the garage...so we have the garage on campus which everybody's able to go in and
use laser printerslaser cutters and all sorts of cool stuff he built a tesla coil...had to
...tesla foils we had sort of snippets of it at the end of the video nobody would let us
...on campus so, we ended up bringing it down to a fire station in the
middle of redmond they didn't have the right kind of our supply there so we rented
...big like ten thousand what generators like
...point twenty-one chick...yes exactly moi.
So, it so we had those running outside and able to record that and,
have that going they're probably going to bring it down to summer nam this
...nashville because they'll let us have it on stage because they don't have anywhere near as much
of electronics on there but like that's somebody in the
maker garage on campus that was their...build this thing
and, creative synthesizer out of it and generally shoot sparks that are eight to ten feet long enough
...at unsuspecting people on the...on all right for american all
quote all coyote devices...each other with so many companies work...different products technologies
and platforms that's probably where all join comes in right definitely, yeah, so,
all join provides a set of standards device profiles
...defining what's called introspection xml and that's really the basis of
interoperability story with all join but as an extension of that
there's the cross-platform code base so regardless of your running art we know or
raspberry pie with windows more with embedded
...ios devices android devices it's a cross-platform
stories
...easy to implement producer functionality which be like a devices you're going
to control or consumer funk functionality which we like and app
...discovered device so we've been like I said built into windows ten we've got to
see api we've got a uw
p api it's a great developer experience on windows ten but we're
...which platform
neuron microcontroller full-fledged high-level operating system?
Those devices can talk to each other and it's not the only technology for interoperability but
it is a great way to reduce this area that's required when you...apps
for interoperability so things like thread and I see these technologies complement each other.
...that on the clouds common pattern that we see is
customers using cloud rendezvous to communicate with different devices and in fact different sort
of submits almost if you if you were like might have a feel
gate gateway speakinga thread and another one speaking all join but,
you want to interoperate between those or extract value from those with
analytics...across the entire fleet on those that's where we really see cloud
...our customers...
With asher I think there's a shorting...question which is that or was
...for coherence that all coyote devices don't talk to each.
You know, you go you buy some ...some home automation...find
...the z wave thing that's the thing this wi-fi thing like they don't
...really hard-hit them all the...were operating from a point of view that says you know,
with our investments that they your teams...altering...devices wanna-be free they want to
talk to each other they want to talk to the cloud and open ways using
...so that's the thing we're pushing on well it's not true today that's where you'll see
as continue to pushes let's get to a place where all devices can just talk to each other
...all devices can just talk to the...and then let's see what people can build when you get rid of all these
...and...there's bridging technologies as well
so it's one thing for every device to be able to talk to every other device directly but,
there's a couple things that are available now that are really interesting your team is built the devices
to bridge which is a way that you can take things like non all
join devices and expose them...as virtual all
drawing devices ad layers of security, you know, that's sort of thing at credentials but,
there's also in the all seen alliance what's called the gateway
...architecture which provides basically away to provide sandbox
local network environment for things like older devices and then...to provide that bridge
...whether...asher or other clouds it's that
...type of scenario where you can access
...for have cloud centric logic so...jump
...question are windows crypto api supported on small devices.
...crypto api is on the device because the devices tend to
be cortex a powered or x eighty-six powered there's plenty of horsepower there to
support cryptography stacked full networking stacks there it's not just it's not just
kind of windows...like literally the same...it's really went.
All right in from and,
...which respirator i-devices good to start...prototype...badger?
...you show this yesterday what did you have up onstage quite a few actually so,
we had arm embed free...board running arm
embed three we had a big one black running able to snappy we also had a raspberry
...running...windows ten-ninety...all those are great how your
sports standard api or standard protocol http and keep
the operator operation there's another question that I just want to address...that I saw a
minute...around whether as your supports bidirectional communication you so,
today we have our bantam service of this been generally available since beginning of
the year ...a it's a great high scale telemetry ingestion service
for doings somewhere north of about eighteen billion messages per day
worldwide through...terms
and one of the things I announced yesterday is that as part of the address of
to suite which is coming out this year ...were also introducing a services part of this week...the
...which also allows not just telemetry ingestion but also
command control has a facility for device identity as well as device,
device registry sequence for device state and then final also...device management
taken manager...chiefly...across...protocols
...and I think it's important to point out that we've been focusing a lot on devices
even so far on this that without the additional support you're talking about without the
command and control without the ability to do mike remote access
...without all of that you don't really have a complete io to solution so it's important that they
...these things all together...when it's great it's great...to start your prototypes sort of
at the device level and,...at once you get the solution
what you have that idea then you start to see a lot of the value coming from
rich analytics across an entire...which is where we see people strategies asher
there's a good question from...with coyote booming what is being done in terms of security and privacy?
Great question so I think sheet
...talk about this on the windows can side I can say from the as your side we have core support all
the rich industry standards from tls to a shared access
a tokens per device as well as key
baltic encryption for encryption all the way through the system we have some strong ideas about some additional
security at a services that will have announcements later this year or as well
on the cloud side we think security is certainly in the cloud
security privacy or absolute tantamount coyote and,
that is very much table...and,
you'll cs not only take industry best practices but also sort of drive that
poured we had a talk yesterday on address ot security fundamentals
...purge...to check that out talks about all the ways that you need to expand
your thinking from just, you know,
devices all the way through software on those devices and bring in the
...security lifecycle on devices but,
I think there's some amazing things coming out of windows
I ot windows coyote definitely adds a lot to the story
that you don't see another platform on the device side I think you just start with
...is a windows desktop to for security and if you think about that as a starting point
...you think about what's in markets they...wow what's
...market today maybe doesn't quite...desktop computers
bar for security you know, lots of cases about baby monitors.
...wi-fi credentials being sent over open...and things, you know,
just kind of stuff like that it's because people are having fun...going faster trying to, you know,
server market and come up with great ideas so we kind of as a first
approximation say okay it's at least as good as a desktop then you kind of
think about what is coyote need device b that's differently are
a couple things one is there's often no interactive user so there's nobody going to type
in username or password...this is a device that...off somewhere so I need a way to securely
I identified this machine not just...user of this machine and if I'm,
for example, communicating to cloud service cloud service need to secure...no yeah,
that really is a message coming from that machine hasn't been spoofs...that software has
...yeah, and, it's a trustworthy machine and,
then getting to that kind of trustworthy machine the other interesting thing about I
...which is different like...laptop up here that maybe I could do interesting things with
variety devices are often unattended just sitting around
in the environment you'll find people that enjoyed the practice of...finding those devices
video popping the plastic off of those devices and going up that's
...sd...we put that my computer and see what I can do with that
...and if that depart hasn't been lock-down with bit locker...the computer doesn't support
...pm it's a real risk...of...so,
these are kind of the things that we're thinking about on the device side in terms of how do we
...you a step further than just kind of pc phone-level...that that's going to be one of the biggest barriers to the
widespread proliferation...devices and...they're not totally
confident about their data and their privacy they're not going to feel comfortable turning that stuff on, you know,
the old band-aid over the webcam type scenario.
I didn't know about...
I do so that's all the time we have today so we're going to wrap up here and thanks for watching.